imagine walking into your I speaking
test confident and prepared knowing no
matter what happens you're going to get
the I score that you need now picture
walking out of the exam Center knowing
that you have got the score that you
deserve this might sound impossible but
it's not I know this because I've helped
thousands of students who are struggling
just like you get a band seven8 or nine
and in this video I'm going to take you
on a journey and tell you exactly what
band five and six students do
differently from band s 7 8 and 9
students and these things that band 7 8
and N students do differently are easy
and simple to learn you'll discover the
hidden traps and common mistakes that
trip up many students and learn the key
techniques that could Skyrocket your
score so if you're ready to go from fear
and stress to just knowing exactly what
to do on test day and having total
confidence keep watching the video so
the I speaking test has three parts so
I've divided this page into three and
we're going to compare what do Buy B
five and six students do very very
differently from ban S 8 and N students
for parts one Parts two and parts three
so let's start off with part one this is
your opportunity to create a great first
impression with the examiner and also
and I think more importantly it allows
you to relax into the test if you relax
into the test in part one you're going
to be much more relaxed and more fluent
throughout the entire test so it is very
very important that you get part one
right so there are three things that
Bond five and six students do
differently from Bond Seven 8 and N9
students and I'd like you to look at
this clip of two students answering the
same question in part one and I want you
to think about which one might be at
about five or about six level and which
one might be at about seven about 9
level um but really think why why are
they at that level not that they sound
more impressive or they have a better
accent or they're using fancier words
what are the things that you could copy
or that you could stop doing that will
really improve your score so I grew up
in Dubai and it's actually one of the um
most populated countries in the GCC um
people come here to visit for tourism
and uh it's actually a good spot for um
uh to visit the largest uh the largest
uh Tower it's called the B khif I'm from
India to be specific I am born and
raised in Delhi and my mom is from
Bombay and my dad is from Kerala but
I've grown up my entire life here in
Delhi and I went to school here went to
University here the first student is
doing something that examiners are
trained to spot this problem creates the
worst first impression and could even
get you about zero and it is
memorized answers so why is this such a
big problem well first of all the ielt
test is not a memorization test it is
testing your ability to communicate
clearly in English not to memorize a
bunch of sentences and repeat them to
the examiner it's also considered
cheating think about it this way if you
really knew how to speak English to the
level that you were trying to get to
would you need to memorize answers no
and it also lowers your score in two
very very important ways it makes you
sound worse listen to this clip and
think about how memorization might have
led to a low score I come from India
India is a very populated country it's
the most populated country in the world
right now and we have lots of cultures
and lots of traditions and we have many
many different languages and uh we also
have different religions and we also
celebrate them very much so did you
notice the first problem I want you to
think back to when you were a child in
school and think back to the lessons
where the teacher got you and the other
students to read out loud from the book
how did you feel do you think that you
sounded fluent or not so fluent this is
exactly how you sound when you memorize
an answer you sound like a robot but
don't worry there's an easy way to fix
that and I'll tell you about it in a
second so did you spot any other issues
let me explain here what the other issue
was so I want you to imagine this is the
destination that you're going for course
you're trying to get to about N9 and we
have here student a and we have here
student B so the examiner asks them tell
me about your hometown student a talks
about the history of their Hometown
culture of their Hometown famous things
in their Hometown the food the weather
the night life and on and on and on
student B just directly answers the
question and this is what the students
do they go off topic and this is why
many of you complain about examiners
constantly interrupt you and stop you
mids sentence it's not because the
examiner is rude in part one they have
to ask you a range of different
questions I think between N9 and 12
different questions and if you're giving
these very very long memorized answers
they're going to stop you in the middle
of your sentence you're going to feel oh
The Examiner thinks I'm doing really
badly you're going to get more stressed
and you're going to sound even more
robotic and your score is going to be
terrible so now you might be thinking
well how long should they actually be
you're saying don't give very long
answers but should I give short answers
that's not good as well no let's look at
what band s and n students actually do
the strategies students at band 7 8 and
N use are incredibly simple for part one
I discovered this when I was teaching in
Saigon in Vietnam and what I used to do
was I would go in maybe 10 or 15 minutes
before the class started and I would
speak to the students about things that
that happened at the weekend or sports
or the weather just normal chitchat
questions that you would talk to a
friend or a work colleague or a teacher
about and during that 10 or 15 minutes
before the class started a lot of
students gave band nine answers then
once the class started I did something
interesting I would get one of the best
students the students that were the most
fluent that were at a ban n level in
those 10 or 15 minutes and I would do a
mock one-on-one speaking task with them
and they would go from band nine to
saying something at the weekend I went
to vau I like seafood they have nice
Seafood it was by the Sea it was nice by
the Sea so from a band nine down to a
band six or seven and I instantly
improved the speaking scores of the
entire class by just saying one thing
why don't you speak in the same way as
you did 10 minutes ago you see in the 10
minutes before class they were talking
to me like a normal human being like a
normal conversation they spoke naturally
like they would to a friend or a work
colleague and they answered the question
directly without going off topic and I
call this test mode students go from
sounding very very fluent to as soon as
the test starts sounding like a robot
but how can you overcome that there's
one simple strategy that band n students
use and I want you to watch these clips
and try and figure out the strategy is
your daily routine different at the
weekend compared to during the week yes
100% so the the weekdays are for work
mainly being productive paying the bills
and the weekends I get to do whatever I
want to do so really treasure and enjoy
my weekends do you prefer to read
magazines or newspapers definitely
magazines um mostly on the topics of
fashion or Interior Design This is what
I really like cuz I like to see creative
sides all from all over the world I like
to see what people are talking about
what's new what's trending and um I like
to learn like I like to have knowledge
of things of like what is this called or
what is that called because usually when
you see pictures you don't usually know
what it's called so when you read a
magazine or where you get the knowledge
that's that's where you get to know oh
this fabric is called this or this uh
decoration is called that so I think
it's very good on information so did you
spot it they simply directly answer the
question and then add a little bit more
detail this detail could be an
explanation or an example a personal
story and if that's confusing or
overwhelming just answer the question
like you would if you were in a coffee
shop with a friend remember they are
testing your ability to speak naturally
in English not to memorize a bunch of
answers and impress The Examiner with
fancy structures so let's now talk about
part two of the speaking test part two
is often the most feared part of the
speaking test because it requires you to
do something that a lot of students are
uncomfortable doing or they're not used
to doing so in part two you'll be given
a q card that looks like this and
they'll ask you to speak about that
topic for up to 2 minutes this can be
quite scary because it's difficult to
speak about anything for 2 minutes
especially in a foreign language when
you're under stress and you have a scary
examiner like me looking at you but what
if I told you it wasn't part two that is
scary it is the strategy that students
use that leads to low scores and what's
also really interesting is when students
stop doing these things that b five and
six students do and they switch to our
strategy that our band 7 eight and N
students use not only do their scores
improve but part two become something
that they look forward to it is their
chance to shine and show the examiner
how great they are without any worry
without any stress first listen to this
student and see if you can spot any
problems with what they're doing
describe some food or drink that you
learned to prepare um I don't really
prepare much food or drink because uh my
wife does most of that for me but uh
food or drink you learn to prepare uh
does uh a cocktail uh kind I know how to
make a Bloody Mary uh when and where you
learn to prepare this um I learned to
prepare it uh one
morning uh when I was thirsty uh how you
learn to prepare it um I just looked up
up YouTube and explain how you felt
about learning to prepare it um I don't
know uh it quenched my thirst so to you
spot what the problem was what most
students do do is they look at the topic
and then they talk about bullet point
number one then bullet point number two
then bullet point number three then
bullet point number four but why is that
a problem well first of all there might
be one or more of these bullet points
that you just don't have much to say
about them so what food was it cocktail
it was a bloody Maria but there's not
much you can really say about that apart
from what the thing is how I learned to
do it again I learned it on YouTube not
a big deal I can't really talk much
about that so it's really limiting the
amount I can talk and remember it is a
test of speaking for up to 2 minutes
then there might be a bullet point that
you just feel uncomfortable talking
about or you don't really know what to
say for that so explain how you felt I
don't really have major feelings about
Bloody Marys and bu cocktails I just
made it up on the spot that makes it
extremely difficult to speak fluently
for up to 2 minutes and then once you
get to the end there after I don't know
20 30 seconds for the average student
you run out of things to say and you're
like oh I've only been talking for 30
seconds I'm going to fail my test and
everything gets worse and worse as you
get more stressed and more stressed so
this is the most common strategy and
what does it lead to poor fluency run
out of things to say and feel like you
failed I've done so many tests with
students who were doing really well in
part one and I was like this student
might be at a band seven or a band eight
and then they use this strategy and
completely fall apart so what do band
7even 8 and N students do differently I
want you to listen to this student who
got a band nine and look at the Q card
and think about what they're doing what
are they doing differently to these B
five and six students food that I
learned to prepare um I'm pescatarian so
I don't eat meat um but I love food and
I have a gluten intolerance so I can't
eat a lot of the Indian food so this is
a little recipe that I learned how to
make which is basically Pan um we call
it cottage cheese in English um it's
like a it's like a spiced tomato base
with cottage
cheese um
with parata Roy but it's made out of
raggi flour which is gluten-free and
super rich in calcium and very good for
people with diabetes although I don't
have diabetes it's very nutritious
basically together it's the perfect meal
keeps you full I I love being healthy I
try to be as healthy as I can so um yeah
that's probably my go-to meal in the
evening cuz I don't have to think about
I have all the ingredients I don't have
to think about how to make it it's kind
of automatic and it's delicious which is
the most important part it's not
compromising on The Taste because I
can't eat salmon and rice every day I
want to eat something that's more um
flavorful and uh nutritious sometimes
when I'm feeling adventurous I like to
eat it with uh yogurt either Greek
yogurt or regular yogurt and add a
couple Indian spices into it and mix it
up so the spiciness of the pan cottage
cheese um the the texture like a drier
stiffer texture of the ragi Roy and the
creaminess and coldness of the yogurt is
match made in heaven so hopefully you
spotted they don't stick to the bullet
points instead what they do is they
focus on the main topic so they're
always talking about the main topic but
they're not necessarily using all of the
bullet points what they do instead is
they have the freedom to add other
bullet points So within that main topic
they are adding things that they feel
more comfortable talking about whilst
talking about that main topic for
example if you got this Q card you might
feel very comfortable talking about
these two bullet points but this third
bullet point is going to take only a few
seconds to talk about and then this
fourth bullet point is something that
you don't really know anything about and
you don't feel comfortable talking about
it but you might find it easy to talk
about other things related to the main
topic such as a description of the main
topic a story how you feel about it
something about the past or something
you hope to do in the future related to
the main topic or any other point that
you feel com comfortable talking about
now should you use all of those ideas no
just the ones that will help you speak
fluently for up to 2 minutes and anyone
that tells you you must talk about each
bullet point in order doesn't know what
they're talking about now let's move on
to in my opinion the most difficult part
of the speaking test part three why is
it so difficult I want you to listen to
these students and think about the
questions don't Focus too much on the
answers but focus on the questions is
being asked and think about how you
might respond to them do you think that
it's better to buy a property or rent a
property no should the same regulations
apply to online advertising everywhere
it you mean the by the regulation um on
the I cannot find the the name how to
say it um let's jump to another question
so as you heard part three questions are
a lot more challenging than the typical
part one question but like everything
with the IELTS test the problem is not
the questions the problem is the
strategy that students use to answer
them so let's start off with the things
that you should not do the most
important thing that you should avoid is
no response if you say to the examiner I
don't know or just nothing comes out of
your mouth or I've even had students
burst out laughing in my face when I ask
them some part three questions what you
are saying to The Examiner is my English
is not good enough to answer this
question but what happens if you really
do have no idea some of these questions
are very very difficult we'll give you a
strategy for how to tackle any question
no matter what the topic is in a second
the second thing that you should never
do is give a short answer and short
answers in part three of the test
normally have nothing to do with your
English level or your speaking skills 15
minutes of talking in a foreign language
in a very stressful situation with
somebody scary and horrible like me
looking at you and judging you is an
exhausting process it is often more
related to fatigue to tiredness than it
is to English ability so what they do is
um something that you should never do is
they surrender they just give up they're
just saying I Surrender I don't want to
answer more of these questions my level
is not as high as you really think it is
but I have some really really good news
for you and this is something that not
many I students know or understand I
think it's a bit of a secret I don't
know whether I should be telling you
this but in part three The Examiner has
lots of different questions that they
could ask you they have some easier
questions and some more difficult
questions if you get a really difficult
question that is an exceptionally good
sign that means that the examiner thinks
that you might be at a band 7even 8 or n
and they're asking you these more
difficult questions to really stretch
your speak ability and separate the band
sevens from the band eights from the
band NES so now that you know if you get
a difficult question that it's a good
thing and you're very happy about it how
do you tackle those difficult questions
the first and most important thing is
always attempt an answer but what if you
have no idea well you could do something
like this I'm not too familiar with the
topic of AI and its relation with the
education however in my knowledge I do
know that AI is developing
more and more and it might be able to
replace some uh teachers jobs or tasks
but it will not replace the trait of
empathy remember it is not a Knowledge
Test it is not an IQ test it is not a
test of how much you know about that
topic it is a speaking test again if you
say nothing what you're telling the
examiner is I don't deserve a high score
but if you attempt an answer even if it
is in that limited way The Examiner will
think okay they might not know much
about that topic let's change topics
let's ask them about something slightly
differently and see how they get on and
you'll probably get something you do
know about but it is far more likely in
part three you will get some kind of a
topic that you do know something about
so how do you shine how do you show The
Examiner that you do deserve a band
seven eight or nine watch this clip and
think about what the student does in
terms of how they structure their answer
what skills does a person person need to
be a great chef M interesting I think I
mean from what I've heard I've never
worked as a chef or worked in a kitchen
before but I think it takes a lot of
trial and error so for that reason I
would imagine that the person would have
to be very patient and with that
patience you need to have an inherent uh
passion for the food that you're making
I think chefs usually specialize in in
one or more
Cuisines um so just having an
understanding of the background of the
spices where it comes from of the meat
where it comes from if you're not
passionate about that it can probably
Tire you out to be that invested in
learning to patience passion and a good
environment like access to good teachers
access to good books access to good
produce would probably help you hone
your craft a lot more so they did four
things here they directly answer the
question they then explained why they
think that or why other people think
that they then backed it up with
examples or you could include a personal
story and then they developed it even
more by showing the other side or you
could give a new point but here's the
most important thing here's the key
lesson for the entirety of the speaking
test what do all of these band 78 or9
students have in common well when you're
talking to a band 78 or9 student it
doesn't doesn't feel like a speaking
test it feels like having a normal
conversation B 78 to n students answer
questions naturally and they do that by
steering the conversation to things that
are easy and comfortable for them to
talk about they don't use tricks or
hacks to try and cheat the test it can't
be cheated instead they use the English
they already have the ability they
already have to clearly communicate
naturally with the examiner and show
them the score they really deserve and
that's how they get the score that they
really deserve but very importantly if
you don't practice all of that you're
never going to be able to do it on test
day so here's a video that gives you
access to more than a thousand I
speaking questions and shows you how to
practice at home for free hope you
enjoyed the lesson and I'll see you
again next time